John H. Talton papers, Inclusive: 1914-1968, undated, Bulk: 1915-1950, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
John H. Talton papers
Inclusive: 1914-1968, undated, Bulk: 1915-1950, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3082
Talton, John H.
1 document box.
The John H. Talton papers contain correspondence, literary productions, financial documents, and ledger books related to the life of John H. Talton, a history professor at Paul Quinn College when it was located in Waco, Texas.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Average.
Biography/Profile
The John H. Talton Papers provide a fascinating insight into the life of one black man who lived in Waco, Texas during the 1920s. John H. Talton was born in Louisiana on 1875 November 22. After some further study on the university level, Talton moved to Texas where he took a job at Paul Quinn College as the foreman of the Mechanical Printing Department. In 1905 he was promoted to the position of History Teacher, and eventually became a professor in the Department of History and Biography where he would remain until 1924. Paul Quinn College was founded in 1872 by the Methodist Episcopal Church, moving to Waco in 1877. Relocated to Dallas in 1990, Paul Quinn College is the oldest African American liberal arts college in Texas.
While in Waco, Talton met his wife Pinkie Althea Talton, who was born in Texas on 1882 September 27. Pinkie was a teacher at A.J. Moore High School in Waco and the two were married by the time of publication of the 1910 Waco City Directory. In 1924, Talton left Paul Quinn to become a grocer. During the 1920s, Talton was also involved with the Mount Moriah Lodge of the Prince Hall Masons in Waco.
John H. Talton died in Waco on 1968 September 11. His wife Pinkie died less than a year later, in 1969 August. Although the details we know about Talton’s life are scarce, his connections to the Mount Moriah Lodge of Prince Hall Masonry and Paul Quinn College make his papers an especially rich collection of resources.
Scope and Content
The John H. Talton papers consist of correspondence, literary productions, financial documents, and ledger books related to the life of John H. Talton. Of particular note are a set of ledger books from the Mount Moriah Lodge of the Prince Hall Masons as well as correspondence and documents related to Paul Quinn College.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid the John H. Talton papers were organized by material type into six folders. Folder titles were preserved when possible.
Currently, the collection is organized into three series: I. Personal, II. Paul Quinn College, and III. Mount Moriah Lodge.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3082. Acquired 1983-03-12
Related Resources
Related references
Hales, Douglass. “Paul Quinn College.” Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2014 May 28.
Find A Grave, Inc. “John H. Talton.” Memorial #95322640. Databases. Accessed 2014 May 28.
Morrison & Fourmy Directory Co. Directory of the City of Waco 1923-1924. Dallas, TX: Morrison & Fourmy Directory Co., 1924. Accessed 2014 May 28.
Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge of Texas. “Who was Prince Hall?” The Most Worshipful Prince Hall Grand Lodge: Free and Accepted Masons of Texas and Its Jurisdiction. Accessed 2014 May 28.
"Texas, Deaths, 1890-1976," index and images. FamilySearch. John Henry Talton, 1968 September 11; citing certificate number 65516, State Registrar Office, Austin; FHL microfilm 2137149. Accessed 2014 May 28.
"United States Social Security Death Index," index, FamilySearch, 1969 August; citing U.S. Social Security Administration, Death Master File, database (Alexandria, Virginia: National Technical Information Service, ongoing). Accessed 2014 May 28.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Paul Quinn College -- History.
Subjects
African American freemasonry -- Texas -- History.; African American universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.; African Americans -- Texas-- History; African-Americans -- Texas -- McLennan County.; Education, Higher -- Texas -- Waco.; Universities and colleges -- Texas -- Waco -- History.
Genres
Correspondence.; Financial records.
- Personal, 1914-1968, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Average.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains correspondence, financial materials, and literary productions relating to the personal life of John H. Talton.
  - Correspondence, 1914-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Financial Materials, 1915-1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Literary Productions: Religious Materials, 1915-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Literary Productions: American Fisheries Society Certificate, 1968 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Literary Productions: The War Cry, 1947 November 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Literary Productions: General, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Paul Quinn College, 1917-1952, undated; 2
  This series contains correspondence and literary productions related to John H. Talton’s work at Paul Quinn College.
  - Literary Productions, 1917-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mt. Moriah Lodge, 1915-1949, undated; 3
  This series contains ledger books and literary productions related to the Mt. Moriah Lodge of the Prince Hall Masons in Waco, Texas.
  - Ledger Book, 1921-1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Record Book, 1923-1927 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ledger Book, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1915-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)